<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prince Henry his first anniversary. By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity, one of his Highnesse chaplaines</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850428</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10053)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 970:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prince Henry his first anniversary. By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity, one of his Highnesse chaplaines</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Prince Henries first anniversarie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177261:1"/>
            <p>PRINCE HENRY HIS FIRST ANNIVERSARY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 11.38.</hi>
               </bibl> Of whom the world was not worthy.</q>
            <p>BY DANIEL PRICE <hi>Doctor in Divinity, one of his Highneſſe Chaplaines.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Joseph Barnes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177261:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father <hi>in God, his Honourable</hi> Dioceſan, <hi>the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> EXETER, <hi>and</hi> Viſitor <hi>of</hi> Exeter College.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reverend <hi>Father,</hi> my duty hath often incited me to performe ſome due <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance</hi> to your <hi>Lordſhip.</hi> Your honourable <hi>care</hi> of our flouriſhing College, hath been my <hi>remembrancer,</hi> &amp; <hi>pleaded</hi> with me as the <hi>Elders</hi> did with our <hi>Saviour,</hi> for the Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion. Hee <hi>is worthy that thou ſhouldſt doe this to him, he loueth vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7.5.</note>
               <hi>and</hi> his predeceſſour <hi>built our ſynagogue.</hi> Your L<hi rend="sup">P</hi>. hath been long, a <hi>painefull, carefull</hi> father, to the <hi>Church,</hi> to our <hi>tribe,</hi> to our <hi>College,</hi> and God hath extraordinarily bleſſed you, that before your <hi>eyes,</hi> your two <hi>eyes,</hi> your two learned, worthy <hi>ſonnes,</hi> in your <hi>dayes,</hi> and in your <hi>Church,</hi> ſerue at the <hi>Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>reaſon,</hi> that I preſume to <hi>preſent</hi> this to your <hi>Honour,</hi> is, becauſe you truly <hi>honoured</hi> him, whom it concernes, that was the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="tcp:177261:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:177261:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:177261:4"/>
               <hi>ornament</hi> of his age <hi>preſent,</hi> and true <hi>mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> to <hi>posteritie.</hi> Your eſpeciall <hi>obſervance</hi> of him, in his life, being made knowne to his <hi>Highneſse,</hi> by the <hi>worthy Gentleman,</hi> my ever ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noured <hi>friend,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Richard Connock,</hi> had beene as truly <hi>rewarded,</hi> as it was <hi>gratiouſly receaued,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d he <hi>liued.</hi> But he is <hi>tranſlated,</hi> and now <hi>raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> in <hi>heaven,</hi> not for a <hi>day</hi> as <hi>Adontah,</hi> or for a <hi>weeke,</hi> as <hi>Zimri,</hi> for a <hi>moneth</hi> as <hi>Shallum,</hi> for ſix months as <hi>Zachary,</hi> for two <hi>yeares</hi> as <hi>Elah,</hi> for three yeares as <hi>Aſa,</hi> for forty yeares as <hi>David,</hi> or fifty fiue as <hi>Manaſses,</hi> but forever and ever, where in time, you ſhall meet him, to remaine with him without all time.</p>
            <p>My ſelfe, with my beſt <hi>devotions</hi> ſhal ever reſt, at your honourable <hi>diſpoſall,</hi> while I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANIEL PRICE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exeter Coll.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. 7.</hi>
                  </date>
                  <hi>The fatall day of</hi> Prince Henries <hi>funerall.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177261:4"/>
            <head>PRINCE HENRIES FIRST ANNIVERSARY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereſoever the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhall bee preached, mention ſhal be made of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 14.9.</note> not only, for loving her <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>life,</hi> when <hi>ſhee</hi> came to <hi>weepe,</hi> to <hi>waſh,</hi> to <hi>wipe</hi> his bleſſed feete, but alſo for that when <hi>he</hi> by whom <hi>ſhee</hi> lived, was dead, and <hi>ſhee,</hi> for whom <hi>he</hi> died, enforcedly left aliue, <hi>ſhee</hi> provided her ointments, for his dead bodies <hi>orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> to pay him the laſt tribute of external duties, of ſepulchral <hi>obſequies.</hi> Her <hi>former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> in the <hi>houſe,</hi> perfumed the <hi>houſe</hi> only, her <hi>later af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> manifeſted at the <hi>graue,</hi> hath perſumed her <hi>memory</hi> through the <hi>world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> A ſinner to annoint her Saviour? It is <hi>ſtrange:</hi> often doth the <hi>heaven,</hi> bath the <hi>earth,</hi> but never did the <hi>earth</hi> bath the heaven, til <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens</hi> teares, yet more ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that though the <hi>life,</hi> yet the <hi>loue</hi> of her <hi>Maiſter</hi> could not <hi>languiſh,</hi> in her colde breſt, though <hi>ſhee</hi> miſſed his heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly <hi>word,</hi> to kindle it, and his bodily <hi>preſence</hi> to cheriſh it, yet <hi>ſhee</hi> followeth through the <hi>ſhadow of death,</hi> at the <hi>croſſe,</hi> and paſſeth to the <hi>chambers of death</hi> at the <hi>graue, poſt funera funus,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177261:5"/>
               <hi>Nichodemus</hi> and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> odors, <note place="margin">Ioh. 19.38.</note> prepared by <hi>art,</hi> and applied by <hi>devotion,</hi> ſhee caſts into the rich <hi>treaſury,</hi> her two mites of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>lamentation,</hi> and giues the world a <hi>checke,</hi> who performeth duties of <hi>loue</hi> only in <hi>life,</hi> and makes <hi>eie Service,</hi> the moſt <hi>harty obſervance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>meditation,</hi> that ſince I conceived, hath <hi>laboured</hi> ſo farre with me that I preſume to bring forth, this <hi>haſty</hi> but <hi>harty</hi> manifeſtation of my boundleſſe <hi>deſires,</hi> &amp; endleſſe <hi>duties</hi> to the memory of that late <hi>gracious,</hi> now <hi>glorious</hi> Prince, beyond all <hi>titles</hi> in his <hi>worth,</hi> all ſorrowes for his <hi>death,</hi> whom no <hi>eie</hi> with <hi>iudgement,</hi> ever beheld, without <hi>raviſhment;</hi> leſt therfore the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> decay, with the <hi>loſſe,</hi> or the <hi>mothe</hi> of <hi>neglect,</hi> infeſt the Princely <hi>veſture</hi> of great <hi>HENRIES</hi> memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſeeing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had his <hi>Pyramis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph. 2. Sam. 18.18.</note> and <hi>Abſolon</hi> his pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and that, in the bad made, worſe kept vow of <hi>Iep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> the daughters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> went yearely, to lament the daughters of <hi>Ieptha.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 11.29.</note> Why ſhould PRINCE HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RYES <hi>Anniverſarie,</hi> bee an eie ſore to any, that are pleaſed with worſe <hi>obiects?</hi> Why ſhould not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our <hi>Ioſias be like the perfume made by the art of the Apothecary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclas. 49.1.</note>
               <hi>ſweet in all mouthes, pleaſing in all minds.</hi> In <hi>favours</hi> done, our <hi>memories</hi> ought to bee <hi>fraile,</hi> but in <hi>benefits</hi> receaued <hi>eternall,</hi> Right deare in the ſight of the <hi>Lord</hi> is the death of his <hi>Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> how much more in the eies of his <hi>Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the death of this <hi>Prince,</hi> ought to be <hi>pretious,</hi> who living was <hi>vertues child, Religions friend,</hi> the <hi>Churches advocate, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths hope,</hi> the <hi>poores Maſter,</hi> and <hi>Gods deare ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177261:5"/>2 <hi>Hune tantum terris fata oſtendere,</hi> Honourable, and renowned plant as the firſt <hi>flowre</hi> of the fig-tree, in the prime, and bloming of his age, hee was <hi>tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> into heauen, and why did not heauen and earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue their <hi>ſtations,</hi> ſunne and moone looſe their <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and ſummer and winter period their <hi>ſeaſons</hi> at this cauſe of ſorrow? What in the <hi>world</hi> ſhall make ſhewe to ſence of <hi>ſtabilitie,</hi> what creature is a fixed <hi>ſtarre,</hi> if ſuch a <hi>Prince</hi> muſt die, whom <hi>beſides</hi> the <hi>by</hi> &amp; <hi>earthly healps</hi> of <hi>drugges</hi> and <hi>amulets,</hi> the divine <hi>hopes</hi> of <hi>vertues, prayers, teares,</hi> &amp; <hi>plaints,</hi> could not keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue: yet <hi>he is</hi> aliue on <hi>earth</hi> in al good mens thoughts, in <hi>heauen</hi> in all Gods ioyes, &amp; though our <hi>eies</hi> cannot now hehold him, becauſe HE is to <hi>bright</hi> a <hi>ſunne,</hi> for our <hi>weake ſight,</hi> our <hi>lookes</hi> muſt be <hi>limited</hi> to a meaner <hi>light,</hi> &amp; we muſt rather humble our ſelues to the <hi>twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> of inferior things then celeſtiall <hi>ſpirits.</hi> To <hi>follow</hi> him in the <hi>pace</hi> that nature <hi>lent</hi> him, his <hi>life</hi> or to the <hi>place</hi> where <hi>nature</hi> left him, his <hi>death,</hi> deſerveth a <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> &amp; <hi>curious</hi> tract, &amp; were rather an <hi>Annall</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, to think hereby, to add to him <hi>repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> that <hi>ſmoaking vapour,</hi> drawne from <hi>earthly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of popular <hi>admiration,</hi> were <hi>frivolous,</hi> neither <hi>profit</hi> to him <hi>dead,</hi> or <hi>approved</hi> of the <hi>wiſe</hi> aliue. To <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> the <hi>cauſe</hi> of doing this, were to <hi>accuſe</hi> the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it, and therefore without <hi>Apollogie,</hi> let this <hi>teſtifie</hi> that I am a <hi>perpetuall votarie,</hi> to the honoured <hi>memorie</hi> of bleſſed PRINCE HENRY, that <hi>whatſoeuer</hi> any other <hi>wants</hi> be, I may not bee <hi>cenſured</hi> for <hi>want</hi> of duty, that ſo while I ſhall runne the <hi>race</hi> of my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177261:6"/>
               <hi>ſinfull</hi> daies, and <hi>continue</hi> the <hi>paſſage</hi> of my <hi>fleeting pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage,</hi> higher <hi>powers</hi> not otherwiſe <hi>diſpoſing</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing</hi> hereat, <note place="margin">Iudg. 11.</note> I may as the <hi>daughters</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> once a yeare, beſtow ſome <hi>odors</hi> or <hi>ointments</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my <hi>Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Maſters <hi>monument,</hi> and burne ſome <hi>incenſe</hi> to his memories <hi>excellence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 All the <hi>world</hi> were ſate, to ſee, &amp; harken, how his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> hopefull, youthfull age ſhould be <hi>employed,</hi> for in HIM, a <hi>glimmering light</hi> of the <hi>Golden</hi> times appeared, all <hi>lines</hi> of expectation met in this <hi>Center,</hi> all <hi>ſpirits</hi> of vertue, <hi>ſcattered</hi> into others were <hi>extrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> into him, <note place="margin">Pliny. Epi. Xenoph. Cy. rop. Fox. Acts &amp; monuments 2. Vol.</note> ſo that if either <hi>Pliny</hi> his teſtimonie of <hi>Traian,</hi> or <hi>Xenophons</hi> deſcription of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> or <hi>Polidor</hi> of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. had beene applyed to HIM, theſe all, and all whatſoever had beene but <hi>ſcannings</hi> &amp; <hi>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> of thoſe high borne, highly-bleſſed vertues in Prince HENRY: His <hi>Magnetique</hi> vertue drewe all the <hi>eies,</hi> and <hi>hearts,</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> world, vpon him who in their ſtricteſt <hi>obſervation,</hi> found how HEE hated <hi>ſinne,</hi> more for the <hi>indignitie</hi> thereof, then for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <hi>danger,</hi> how he ſtood like a <hi>Center,</hi> vnmoved, the <hi>circumference</hi> of his eſtate, being drawne aboue, beneath, about him, how hee lived without the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe</hi> of an <hi>adverſarie,</hi> his Perſon being as a <hi>Saint,</hi> his Court as a <hi>Temple,</hi> there was nothing, but hee deſired to knowe but <hi>moſt</hi> and <hi>firſt</hi> himſelfe, and not ſo much, his owne <hi>ſtrength</hi> as his owne <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> al <hi>ingredients</hi> of beauty, <note place="margin">Nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixtie &amp; nine yeares. Gen. 5.27.</note> concurred to the making vp of his <hi>body,</hi> in which, a <hi>ſoule</hi> might haue contented it ſelfe to liue an age, yea, were it <hi>Methuſulahs:</hi> and for his <hi>ſoule,</hi> as if the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177261:6"/>
               <hi>tincture</hi> and <hi>tainture</hi> of originall ſinne, had not much infected it, it was the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of all <hi>vertue,</hi> in which <hi>Pietie</hi> had her <hi>Oratory, Religion</hi> her <hi>Sanctuarie, Prayer</hi> her <hi>Cenſor,</hi> all Acts of devotion their <hi>alter,</hi> &amp; his <hi>altar,</hi> the plentifull daily offering, of <hi>Almes-giuing.</hi> Future <hi>ages</hi> declining, as well in their <hi>being,</hi> as <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> will ſtand <hi>amaſed,</hi> at his <hi>storie,</hi> whoſoever ſhall build it, that a <hi>Prince</hi> ſo <hi>noble</hi> and ſo <hi>humble,</hi> ſo <hi>valiant,</hi> and ſo <hi>patient</hi> ſo <hi>Heroicall</hi> in his exerciſe, and ſo <hi>Angelicall</hi> in his prayers, ſo abundantly <hi>liberall</hi> in his beſtowing, &amp; ſo honorably <hi>frugall</hi> in managing his eſtate, ſo like to <hi>liue,</hi> and ſo <hi>content</hi> to die, ſo <hi>faithfull</hi> to his <hi>God, dutiful</hi> to his <hi>royall parents, mercifull</hi> to <hi>poore, gratefull</hi> &amp; <hi>grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to all, either ſhould haue beene ſo <hi>ſoone,</hi> ſo <hi>good,</hi> or be ſo ſoone, ſo <hi>forgot.</hi> There is no honeſt <hi>ſubiect</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw him, but will forever care to <hi>carry</hi> the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of his <hi>Princely</hi> feature in their beſt compoſed <hi>memory,</hi> his piercing <hi>eye,</hi> gratious <hi>ſmile,</hi> graue <hi>frowne,</hi> and divine <hi>face</hi> compoſed of <hi>modeſty</hi> and <hi>maieſtie.</hi> How ſlow he was to <hi>anger,</hi> quicke to <hi>apprehend,</hi> how ſpeedy to <hi>pardon,</hi> how magnificent in <hi>building,</hi> munificent in <hi>entertaining,</hi> how conſtant in his <hi>ſtudies,</hi> &amp; paramou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in all rare <hi>inventions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learne then from hence all yee wandring Drones, whoſe life is a continuall <hi>ſleepe,</hi> or worſe a ſleeping <hi>death,</hi> of whom no <hi>memorie</hi> or <hi>monument</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine but as that of beaſts, <hi>fuerunt,</hi> yee whoſe ſole knowledge is only the Philoſophy of <hi>Epicuriſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut.</note> yee whoſe memory ſhall rot among the <hi>poſterities,</hi> yee who are entiſed by the <hi>ſubtiltie,</hi> and entrapped in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177261:7"/>
               <hi>ſnares</hi> of Sathan, who vſeth every of you for ſome <hi>end,</hi> and leadeth all of you in the <hi>end</hi> to finall <hi>deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> How apparant is it to all, that the <hi>Drunkard</hi> is his <hi>butler,</hi> the <hi>Glutton</hi> his <hi>Cooke,</hi> the <hi>Adulterer</hi> his <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> the <hi>Slanderer</hi> his <hi>Lawyer,</hi> the <hi>Vſurer</hi> his <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,</hi> the <hi>Ieſuit</hi> his <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> and ſhall the ſame <hi>intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> beguile you? Be there ſo few <hi>good,</hi> as that, when but 4 in the <hi>world</hi> a <hi>Caine,</hi> when that number doubled, and eight were in the <hi>Arke,</hi> a <hi>Cham,</hi> when that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>trebled</hi> in twelue <hi>Apoſtles</hi> a <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> knowing his time <hi>ſhort,</hi> hath provided his <hi>factors,</hi> in all <hi>places</hi> for all <hi>occaſions,</hi> Popiſh <hi>traitours,</hi> and apiſh <hi>flatterers</hi> often about <hi>Court, Hypocrits and Loiterers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>City, buyers</hi> and <hi>ſellers</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> every where ſwarming <hi>Locuſts,</hi> and the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> ſo wiſe in their <hi>generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſo buſily <hi>imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and taking ſuch paines to goe to <hi>hell.</hi> How ſhould theſe thoughts, drawe and driue yee out of that as <hi>hatefull,</hi> as <hi>harmefull</hi> neglect of doing wel, &amp; ſtirre yee to ſtriue to do ſome good <hi>acceptable</hi> to God, <hi>profitable</hi> to man, <hi>available</hi> to your owne <hi>ſoules,</hi> that not only in the day of <hi>retribution,</hi> a recompence, but in this <hi>world,</hi> there may be a <hi>remembrance</hi> of you, as in every <hi>place</hi> there now is, of this <hi>wonder</hi> of his <hi>time</hi> and mirror of <hi>Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Whoſe <hi>Religious ſoule,</hi> did ſo truely entertaine the <hi>Patronage</hi> and protection of <hi>religion,</hi> that as HEE hated <hi>Poperie</hi> with a perfect hate, ſo his <hi>loue</hi> vnto <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> as it <hi>ſhined outwardly,</hi> ſo did it <hi>burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> in his owne <hi>practiſe,</hi> in which, beſides his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177261:7"/>
               <hi>zeale</hi> to God, and <hi>loue</hi> to good men, he was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>carefull</hi> of <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> leſſon to number his <hi>daies,</hi> never <hi>deſiring</hi> to liue long, nay, <note place="margin">Pſal 90.</note> often vſing con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temptible <hi>ſpeeches</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> of <hi>bravery,</hi> of <hi>beautie,</hi> accounting long <hi>life</hi> not only <hi>vanitie</hi> but <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie,</hi> and on the <hi>contrary,</hi> many, and <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>heavenly</hi> were his frequent <hi>meditations</hi> vpon the <hi>certaintie</hi> of <hi>ſalvation, immortalitie</hi> of the <hi>ſoule, reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>dead,</hi> and <hi>ioy</hi> of the <hi>bleſſed,</hi> as thoſe neere about his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> can teſtifie, by thoſe his wiſe, and divine <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothegmes,</hi> which will never be <hi>razed</hi> out of their <hi>moſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> reſerved memories. Wherein, I cannot omit his eſpeciall regard of <hi>honeſt Sermons,</hi> for that was the title he <hi>attributed</hi> to <hi>ſharp,</hi> and <hi>ſound ſermons</hi> which neither favored of <hi>flattery</hi> or <hi>Poperie,</hi> among which, as none ever paſſed without his reverent <hi>attention,</hi> and remarkeable <hi>obſervation,</hi> ſo eſpecially in two <hi>preached</hi> before his <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> though ſome yeares in <hi>diſtance,</hi> yet in the ſame month of his <hi>finall</hi> and <hi>fatall ſickneſſe.</hi> The firſt at <hi>Richmond,</hi> in <hi>October 1608.</hi> vpon that text which afterwards, <note place="margin">Pſal. 82. v. 6.7.</note> was as a box of <hi>spikenard</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noint his body at the <hi>buriall,</hi> choſen by the moſt <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend</hi> father, the <hi>L. Archb.</hi> his grace at the <hi>funerall:</hi> Pſal. 82.6.7. <hi>I haue ſaid yee are Gods and yee are all childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the moſt high, But yee ſhall die like men, and fall like one of the Princes,</hi> which <hi>Text</hi> being entreated on, at <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> by one of his highneſſe <hi>Chaplaines,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waiting, and the <hi>Text</hi> called the <hi>Fall of the leafe,</hi> howſoever the <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> were one of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> &amp; youngeſt of that <hi>name</hi> &amp; <hi>number,</hi> yet it pleaſed his <hi>highneſſe</hi> to require
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177261:8"/>a <hi>coppy,</hi> thereof, and as with <hi>Princely</hi> patience to <hi>heare,</hi> ſo with godly <hi>diligence</hi> to <hi>recall</hi> ſome paſſages therein that <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Libanon, Roſes of the field, Lillies</hi> of the <hi>Vallyes, Princes, ſtarres</hi> &amp; <hi>Angels</hi> had <hi>fallen,</hi> that <hi>humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>mortallity</hi> were twinnes, that all <hi>fleſh</hi> was as a <hi>flowre,</hi> and the <hi>grace</hi> thereof as the <hi>graſſe</hi> of the field, &amp;c. The other <hi>Sermon,</hi> as if it were provided, againſt the day of his <hi>preparation</hi> by that all <hi>guiding</hi> eie of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M Wilkinſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon Octob. 25. 1612.</note> was <hi>learnedly</hi> &amp; <hi>powerfully</hi> delivered in <hi>S. Iames</hi> chappell by a <hi>Reverend</hi> divine, Chaplaine to the kings <hi>Maieſty</hi> vpon the <hi>Sabaoth</hi> day of his highneſſe <hi>ſickning</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> being taken from <hi>Iob. 14.1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 14.1.</note>
               <hi>Man that is borne of a woman, is ſhort of daies and full of troubles,</hi> wherein, by the miſerable <hi>entry,</hi> of man into the <hi>world</hi> his <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and ſpeedy <hi>paſſage,</hi> out of the <hi>world,</hi> and his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>pilgrimage</hi> and <hi>indurance</hi> while, he is in the <hi>world</hi> he ſtirred <hi>all,</hi> of all <hi>eſtates</hi> to the <hi>conſideration</hi> of their <hi>states,</hi> and did much affect his <hi>highneſſe,</hi> as appeared both by his great <hi>attention</hi> and <hi>commendation</hi> thereof. Bleſſed <hi>Prince</hi> by this, <note place="margin">Eſay. 38 1.</note> preparing as <hi>Heſekias</hi> was war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſet his houſe in <hi>order,</hi> becauſe he muſt die.</p>
            <p>Learne hence, <hi>yee Courtly Gallants,</hi> yee, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogue the tearme of your <hi>lifes</hi> &amp; as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpake, <note place="margin">Zephany.</note>
               <hi>yee that put farre from you the day of the Lord,</hi> ſet your houſes in <hi>order,</hi> you <hi>muſt die,</hi> an account muſt be <hi>made,</hi> did yee but know what houre the <hi>theefe</hi> Death, will come, yee would <hi>watch,</hi> if at that <hi>time,</hi> the houſe bee not built by <hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>built</hi> and not prepared by <hi>hope,</hi> or prepared and not ſwept by <hi>repentance</hi> or <hi>ſwept</hi> for a <hi>time,</hi> and not <hi>dayly,</hi> ſet in <hi>order</hi> by meditation of <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177261:8"/>If there be no care of the ſpirituall <hi>Oeconomy</hi> at that <hi>day,</hi> at that <hi>houre,</hi> yee ſhall drinke the bitter <hi>cuppe</hi> of the <hi>dregges</hi> of deſtruction. O then al of <hi>yee,</hi> that <hi>eat,</hi> as if yee <hi>did not</hi> care to <hi>liue,</hi> and yet <hi>build,</hi> as if yee <hi>did</hi> not thinke to <hi>die,</hi> yee that preferre <hi>Hagar</hi> before <hi>Sara,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. Gen. 16 3. Gen. 30.4.</note> and neglect <hi>Rahel</hi> in regard of <hi>Bilha,</hi> yee, that reſpect not, that poore, pining, fainting <hi>Inmate</hi> the <hi>ſoule,</hi> ſtand in your <hi>watchtowers,</hi> looke towards the <hi>vveſt</hi> to the ſetting of the <hi>ſunne,</hi> diſpoſe of your <hi>bodies</hi> &amp; your <hi>ſoules,</hi> that your <hi>eyes</hi> may ſee your <hi>ſalvation. One</hi> put his barnes in order, and that night they tooke away his ſoule; <hi>Achitophel</hi> put his <hi>houſe</hi> in order, and that day, he <hi>went</hi> and <hi>hanged</hi> himſelfe; <note place="margin">Eſay 38.1.</note> but <hi>Heſekias ſet his houſe in order,</hi> ſet his <hi>ſoule</hi> in order, and ſo recovered <hi>health</hi> to <hi>body,</hi> and <hi>ſoule. Princes</hi> doe partake of a <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>omnipotency,</hi> their braue <hi>followers,</hi> potentate <hi>friends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beaux.</note> maieſticke <hi>roabes,</hi> treaſured vp <hi>riches,</hi> delicate <hi>fare,</hi> faire <hi>Palaces,</hi> pleaſures, as if <hi>Paradiſe</hi> were <hi>recovered,</hi> &amp; their <hi>delights,</hi> as if <hi>heaven</hi> were come to dwell on <hi>earth,</hi> as the <hi>nation</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> cary with them a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> of their ſtained <hi>ſtemme,</hi> &amp; murtherous progeny, ſo all theſe <hi>vanities</hi> cary a ſent and ſhew of <hi>earthly</hi> &amp; periſhing <hi>mortalitie. Sorrow, ſickneſſe, death,</hi> be <hi>Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and of great <hi>command,</hi> they haue their <hi>groomes</hi> in every office of the <hi>houſe.</hi> To ſay no <hi>more,</hi> If <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his royalty did remember his <hi>Creator</hi> in the daies of his <hi>youth,</hi> before the evill <hi>dayes</hi> came, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note> before the yea s drew nigh, wherein hee might ſay, <hi>I had no pleaſure therein;</hi> then <hi>linger</hi> no <hi>longer,</hi> whoſoever thou art, in the <hi>morning ſowe thy ſeed,</hi> worke <hi>while it is day,</hi> provide
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177261:9"/>with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the barnes before the <hi>famine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41. Gen. 6.13. Luk. 15.11. Luk. 16.1.</note> and with <hi>Noah</hi> the Arke before the <hi>flood.</hi> Let the <hi>prodigall</hi> child, <hi>vniuſt ſteward, vnwiſe virgin,</hi> ſerue thee, as <hi>examples</hi> to terrifie thee. But, to incite <hi>thee,</hi> &amp; to <hi>rowſe</hi> vp that <hi>panting fainting</hi> breath, of thy <hi>ſoule; Remember</hi> the carefull <hi>reſolution</hi> of this rare <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe <hi>min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadge</hi> may lend character to all the <hi>world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 When the <hi>ſunne</hi> of his Highneſſe life, was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to the <hi>meridian,</hi> his, and our <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> began, &amp; before the <hi>noone-tide</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> the <hi>night</hi> of <hi>death</hi> ſet vpon him. When all the worlds Eccho of him was that, which <hi>Antigonus</hi> ſpake of <hi>Pyrrhus, maximum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum ſi ſeneſceret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pluz.</note> then did that great <hi>Tyrant</hi> death firſt <hi>beate,</hi> then <hi>batter</hi> all the <hi>naturall</hi> forces, all the <hi>principall</hi> parts of his bodily <hi>fortreſſe.</hi> The beſiege was not <hi>long,</hi> but <hi>cruell,</hi> when HEE forecaſting the worſt of <hi>events</hi> and <hi>encountering</hi> them before they <hi>came,</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried this <hi>character</hi> of the <hi>valiant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Hall Char. of val.</note> often to looke death in the <hi>face,</hi> and with a religious <hi>conſtancie,</hi> to paſſe by it with a <hi>ſmile,</hi> at once, ſhewing both his <hi>content,</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> of death.</p>
            <p>O you vaine froathy <hi>fondlings</hi> of the world, who are <hi>enimies</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> in whom <hi>cuſtome</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> hath left no <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>ſhame,</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> of life, no <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>death; learne</hi> hence, and <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> at the <hi>leſſon,</hi> what it is, to walke <hi>early,</hi> and <hi>dayly,</hi> with your <hi>maker,</hi> &amp; learne, what it is to provide <hi>deaths payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> before the <hi>day.</hi> Shall he that was <hi>Natures mir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour,</hi> the <hi>delight</hi> and <hi>delicacy</hi> of <hi>mankind,</hi> being as <hi>deere</hi> to the <hi>world,</hi> as <hi>heauen deare</hi> to him, ſhall HE ſo <hi>ballace</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:177261:9"/>himſelfe with holy <hi>wiſdome,</hi> that he <hi>provides</hi> to <hi>floate</hi> ſteddily in the midſt of his <hi>tempeſtuous</hi> ſhipwrack? ſhal he, in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> heate of <hi>blood, beautie</hi> of <hi>youth,</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>time,</hi> prepare ſo timely, at once, both to <hi>welcome</hi> and <hi>contemne</hi> death? And will yee, yee earthly <hi>Glowormes,</hi> neglect ſo certaine <hi>vncertaine</hi> a point of <hi>ſtate,</hi> as the <hi>prevention</hi> of death, by <hi>proviſion</hi> for death? your <hi>daily</hi> ſurfets, <hi>nightly</hi> riots, <hi>hourely</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels are attended, not only with <hi>ſurquedry</hi> but <hi>mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> If ever <hi>place,</hi> or <hi>age, time,</hi> or <hi>perſon,</hi> had had a <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> or <hi>immunitie</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>death,</hi> then yee might continue to flatter your ſelues, and to <hi>betray</hi> your <hi>ſoules:</hi> but whenas all that <hi>ſoiourne</hi> vpon the face of the <hi>earth</hi> muſt returne into the <hi>wombe</hi> and <hi>tombe</hi> of the earth, that the <hi>Arkes</hi> of your <hi>bodies,</hi> bee full of <hi>holes,</hi> and yee take water at a <hi>thouſand</hi> breaches; when that <hi>art</hi> of <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> the duell whereof the <hi>divell</hi> is the <hi>Maſter,</hi> is ſo <hi>frequent,</hi> that beyond the ancient (but abhorrent) ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of <hi>humane murthers,</hi> as the <hi>infants</hi> of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> in the <hi>cradles, Eglon</hi> in the <hi>parlour, Saul</hi> in the <hi>mountaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2.16. Iudg. 3.12. 1. Sam. 26. 2. Chr. 32.21.</note>
               <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> on his <hi>bed, Zenaeherib</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places whatſoever, <hi>forraine</hi> and <hi>domeſticke,</hi> ſtream with the blood of <hi>ſingle</hi> combat, of which bloody <hi>iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue,</hi> your ſelues be the <hi>Authors,</hi> the <hi>actors,</hi> the <hi>abettors;</hi> To which, adde the <hi>nameleſſe</hi> and <hi>helpleſſe</hi> infirmities, by <hi>outrages</hi> and <hi>ſickneſſes,</hi> wherevnto yee are ſubiect. And vpon this <hi>conſideration,</hi> turne your eyes <hi>inwardes</hi> into your owne <hi>Anatomies,</hi> obſerue whether yee need <hi>Cautions</hi> in this kind, that ſeeing <hi>examples</hi> moue not, <hi>precepts</hi> may prevaile.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:177261:10"/>6 But whither <hi>goe I?</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Prince!</hi> he was both an apt <hi>ſcholler</hi> and an excellent <hi>Maſter,</hi> his <hi>vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> was <hi>illumined</hi> with the <hi>beames</hi> of divine <hi>truth, God</hi> acquainted him with his <hi>word,</hi> and in his <hi>word</hi> with his <hi>will.</hi> Hee made ſure for his <hi>ſoule,</hi> &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it no <hi>ſafety,</hi> to bee vnſetled in the <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> of his <hi>finall</hi> eſtate. How were the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout</hi> and frequent <hi>obſervations</hi> of his morning <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> offices, without <hi>interceſsion,</hi> privately continued, as if with <hi>David</hi> he had vowed, <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note>
               <hi>My voice ſhalt thou heare in the morning O Lord, in the morning will I direct my praier vnto thee.</hi> This our <hi>morning ſtarre,</hi> preventing the <hi>morning watch</hi> in his <hi>morning offring,</hi> as if to him, <hi>Omnis dies eſſet vltimus dies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1. Pſ. 55.18. Rupertus, Vitriacus. Bon avent. Auſt. in Pſal. Veſpere Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, mane in reſurrectione meridie in aſcenſione: enarrabo ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpere patien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morientis annuntiabo mane vitam reſurgentis, orabo vt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audiat meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſedens ad dextram Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris. Sanctuary of ſoule.</note> ſo did he ſeaſon &amp; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelfe, &amp; as <hi>Iob</hi> ſacrificed to ſanctifie his ſonnes, ſo did he pray, againſt his <hi>ſinnes,</hi> &amp; commune with his owne heart in his <hi>chamber</hi> and was <hi>still;</hi> and thought not this enough, but that with <hi>David,</hi> more <hi>fervently,</hi> more <hi>frequently, he would praiſe the Lord in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> and that, as that holy <hi>prophet</hi> profeſſeth, <hi>inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> yea and <hi>continually, veſpere, mane, meridie,</hi> in the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, evening,</hi> and <hi>at noone,</hi> did he praiſe the <hi>Lord,</hi> not <hi>only,</hi> as ſome interpreters iudge, becauſe theſe three parts of the <hi>day,</hi> were <hi>conſecrated</hi> by thoſe three <hi>prime</hi> acts of our redemption, the <hi>evening</hi> by Chriſts <hi>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the <hi>morning</hi> by his <hi>reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; the <hi>noone</hi> by his <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Aſcenſion,</hi> but alſo becauſe theſe times haue <hi>alwaies</hi> by the faithfull of all <hi>ages</hi> beene hallowed by divine <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons,</hi> and therefore in <hi>chamber</hi> and <hi>cloſet,</hi> our <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved theſe, <hi>knowing,</hi> that <hi>actions</hi> both of <hi>difficultie</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177261:10"/>and <hi>weight,</hi> are drawne to <hi>perfection</hi> by <hi>often</hi> vſe. And <hi>therefore</hi> ſeeing it is a very hardmatter, either to <hi>praie,</hi> or to <hi>die,</hi> either <hi>willingly,</hi> or <hi>well,</hi> all ought both <hi>timelie</hi> and <hi>diligently</hi> to exerciſe themſelues, that by <hi>praying often,</hi> and ſo conſequently, by <hi>dying</hi> often, in the end, men may both <hi>pray,</hi> and <hi>die, eaſily</hi> and <hi>willingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O then all yee <hi>drowſie Night-birds!</hi> ariſe from your beds of <hi>ſloth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.8.</note> cary the <hi>watch</hi> of praier be <hi>vigilant</hi> over your owne ſoules, looke vpon the <hi>pale horſe,</hi> and him that <hi>ſitteth thereon,</hi> whoſe name is <hi>death. Provide,</hi> that yee be not ſodainely <hi>ſurpriſed,</hi> and <hi>dy</hi> before yee begin to <hi>liue.</hi> It is weakneſſe to be <hi>vnwilling,</hi> to that which is <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be <hi>done,</hi> it is <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>die,</hi> and it is <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> for dying <hi>well, often</hi> to pray, <hi>often</hi> to meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy <hi>death.</hi> A <hi>day wil come,</hi> when thy evening ſhal be <hi>ſhut</hi> vp, be thou <hi>mighty,</hi> thou canſt not <hi>reſist,</hi> be thou <hi>rich,</hi> thou canſt not <hi>corrupt,</hi> be thou never ſo <hi>wiſe,</hi> thou canſt neither <hi>appeaſe</hi> nor <hi>avoid</hi> DEATH. Which in the principall <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> of <hi>age, plungeth</hi> the thoughts of the <hi>worldly, interrupteth</hi> the <hi>enterpriſes</hi> of the <hi>worthy,</hi> breaketh the <hi>ſtudies</hi> of the <hi>learnedſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth</hi> of the flowriſhing <hi>hopes</hi> of the <hi>faireſt,</hi> the ſame God telleth <hi>Princes,</hi> yee are Gods, <hi>et homines coeleſtibus aequat,</hi> and yet they ſhall die like men, <hi>ſceptra ligonibus aequat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Which <hi>meditation</hi> extracted by the <hi>Limbique of contemplation</hi> into <hi>vertuous action, indued</hi> and <hi>endow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed</hi> our <hi>PRINCE,</hi> with an <hi>humble holy</hi> patience in all the ſtormy invaſions of his <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> having ſo conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>himſelfe,</hi> as ſorrowes could not <hi>conquer</hi> him, his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177261:11"/>
               <hi>experiments,</hi> ſage for their <hi>truth,</hi> though young for their <hi>time,</hi> had drawne out rules of <hi>confidence,</hi> and <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which he did oppoſe, againſt all the <hi>feares</hi> of <hi>diſtruſt:</hi> he knew whom he <hi>truſted,</hi> and how <hi>farre</hi> death could lead <hi>him,</hi> his <hi>ſhield</hi> was of a <hi>mettall,</hi> not ſo <hi>hard,</hi> as <hi>flexible,</hi> &amp;, as it was never <hi>miſsed,</hi> ſo never <hi>pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,</hi> he both <hi>ſaw,</hi> &amp; <hi>endured</hi> a divine <hi>hand</hi> inviſibly ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and in thoſe ſenſible <hi>ſcourges</hi> he did not <hi>murmur.</hi> His hopes were ſo <hi>ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,</hi> that they inſult over the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>diſcouragements,</hi> his <hi>apprehenſions</hi> ſo <hi>deepe</hi> that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he once <hi>faſtened,</hi> he ſooner left his <hi>life</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his <hi>hould,</hi> his holy <hi>patience</hi> invincible, as full of <hi>faith,</hi> as void of <hi>fury,</hi> being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue <hi>nature</hi> when <hi>below himſelfe,</hi> his <hi>paines, faintings, heats, toſſings,</hi> &amp; <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vulſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> not able to diſtract his <hi>perſon,</hi> or diſturb his <hi>patience.</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after a lingring, growing encreaſing <hi>poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of ſome peſtilent <hi>humor, ſickneſſe</hi> had <hi>ſurpriſed</hi> his head, <note place="margin">Laur. Anat.</note>
               <hi>Sacram Palladis arcem,</hi> the watchtower of the whole body, <hi>domicilium &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum propugnaculum,</hi> as <hi>Laurentius</hi> calleth it; yet his <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> increaſed with his <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> &amp; with a <hi>tongue</hi> calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>free,</hi> a <hi>forhead Socrates-like reſolute</hi> and firme, &amp; with a ſetled <hi>countenance,</hi> he conſults the <hi>Pilots</hi> of his bodily <hi>veſsell,</hi> and in their <hi>diſtraction,</hi> while he <hi>ſuffers</hi> and is <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> and <hi>beholders</hi> pitie him, and his <hi>torments</hi> cannot <hi>diſeaſe</hi> him, he refers all <hi>peaceably,</hi> patiently, to the will of his <hi>maker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch.</note> as if hee had learned that leſſon of <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius, Oramus Domine fiat volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tas tua, facta eſt, feramus.</hi> In all this, when not <hi>maſter</hi> of his <hi>health,</hi> yet <hi>maſter</hi> of <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſubduing <hi>paſſion</hi> to <hi>reaſon,</hi> &amp; bowing to beare the <hi>burden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> he verified that of <hi>Bernard, Submittitur ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177261:11"/>non amittitur, nec deeſt dolor, ſed ſuperatur, ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learne hence yee <hi>impatient</hi> and <hi>paſſionate whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds,</hi> yee, who hoiſe vp <hi>ſailes</hi> in your <hi>tempests,</hi> whoſe <hi>words</hi> be <hi>wounds,</hi> &amp; breath <hi>blood,</hi> behold (but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out amazement) a Princely <hi>ſoules</hi> calme, in the midſt of a bodily <hi>ſtorme,</hi> whoſe <hi>reſolution</hi> was, as that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Tertullian, Totum licet ſeculum pereat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note>
               <hi>dum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiam lucrifaciam,</hi> rather would hee, that the world ſhould <hi>periſh</hi> vnto him, then his <hi>patience</hi> periſh. <hi>Learne</hi> if yee are not as farre paſt the boundes of <hi>nature,</hi> as <hi>grace,</hi> yee fiery <hi>monſters,</hi> who as if yee were borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>torrid zone,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſpleneticall, phreneticall</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, like the <hi>ſurges</hi> of the <hi>ſea,</hi> breake the <hi>veſſels</hi> of your <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> and <hi>reaſon;</hi> who are ſtirred with leſſe then a word, and are more <hi>turbulent</hi> then a <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> who in the leaſt <hi>diſaſters</hi> are ready to blaſpheme <hi>God</hi> and die, whoſe <hi>proceedings</hi> are as <hi>heady,</hi> as your words <hi>haſty,</hi> and lookes <hi>peremptory,</hi> who never looke how <hi>innocent,</hi> but how <hi>ſtrong</hi> yee are, and will rather <hi>vſher,</hi> then <hi>ſmother</hi> an iniurie, making your ſword the firſt of <hi>tryals,</hi> &amp; <hi>murther</hi> the fruit of the ſword, whoſe <hi>ſocietie</hi> admits no <hi>ſafetie,</hi> nor <hi>acquaintance</hi> any <hi>tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</hi> O yee <hi>bloodhounds,</hi> is the life of man no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, or the iuſtice of God for <hi>blood</hi> no more <hi>rigorous,</hi> that without reſpect, I ſay not of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but <hi>Pagan</hi> patience, yee familiarly deſtroy your <hi>brethren,</hi> for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath died? Yee <hi>poſterity</hi> and tribe of <hi>Cain,</hi> when any <hi>ſmall</hi> diſgrace, nay the leaſt <hi>diſtaſt,</hi> a <hi>tale,</hi> a <hi>toy,</hi> a <hi>breath,</hi> a <hi>word,</hi> a <hi>ſyllable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The lye.</note> will edge to <hi>revengefull</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:177261:12"/>impatience, behold him, <hi>holy</hi> ſoule, from whom al his <hi>paines,</hi> redoubling of his <hi>pangs,</hi> the <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> of <hi>humours,</hi> in his troubled <hi>heart,</hi> tormented <hi>head,</hi> parched <hi>tongue,</hi> ſchortched <hi>throat,</hi> inflamed <hi>body,</hi> and fired <hi>blood,</hi> could not extort any <hi>ſparkes</hi> of impatient <hi>paſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 Thus, in him never was <hi>divorce</hi> between devotion &amp; patience. Holy ſoule! how prevalent was <hi>devotion</hi> in him, by which hee caſt ſo often <hi>ſweet wood</hi> into his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>waters!</hi> how did Gods ſpirit by this ſubdue <hi>his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> regenerate his <hi>will,</hi> purifie his <hi>nature,</hi> how by this, in his <hi>extremitie</hi> hourely did he walke with his <hi>maker,</hi> and talke with him <hi>familiarly,</hi> celeſtial ſpirits affording him <hi>company</hi> and ſervice, all the <hi>roomes</hi> of his holy <hi>hart</hi> ſet a part for <hi>holineſſe!</hi> Which <hi>habit</hi> was obtained by the former <hi>acquiſition</hi> of it, in thoſe many vertuous <hi>actions</hi> of his tender <hi>age,</hi> when in the 14 <hi>yeare</hi> of his <hi>time,</hi> he approved himſelfe to be a <hi>religious hearer, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious</hi> obſerver, and <hi>obſequious</hi> obeyer of the word of his <hi>maker,</hi> his gracefull <hi>gravitie,</hi> giving much <hi>life</hi> to thoſe <hi>ſermons,</hi> which were <hi>heard</hi> by him, but his <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> much more. Among many others this one <hi>remarkable monument</hi> ſhall reſt with <hi>renowne</hi> vpon his <hi>memorie,</hi> he abhorred an <hi>oath,</hi> laying, beſides the <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liske</hi> of <hi>imputation,</hi> a pecuniary <hi>mulct</hi> vpon thoſe his <hi>followers</hi> and <hi>family,</hi> who were found faulty in <hi>ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> which monies were duly <hi>diſtributed,</hi> to the <hi>poore.</hi> Neither can I here omit his <hi>religious</hi> anſwer made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, that <hi>wondred,</hi> at his <hi>ſports,</hi> to obſerue his <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe freedome</hi> from <hi>oathes,</hi> hee anſweres, <hi>I never knew
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177261:12"/>any ſport worth an oath.</hi> This <hi>holineſſe</hi> ſo early <hi>began,</hi> ended not, ſickneſſe <hi>diſeaſed it not,</hi> ſorrow <hi>diſordred</hi> it not. He ſhewed his owne care of <hi>ſerving</hi> God then, in his daily <hi>calling</hi> vpon him, <hi>commanding</hi> in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of his <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> that the ordinary <hi>howres</hi> &amp; <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> in his Cloſet ſhould be duly obſerved, as if hee had <hi>derived</hi> pietie, as well as <hi>royaltie</hi> from <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, whoſe ſpeech was, <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15.</note>
               <hi>I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord;</hi> beſides the <hi>prayers</hi> which often he deſired to bee vſed at his <hi>highneſſe</hi> bed-ſide, wherein a learned and <hi>Reverend</hi>
               <note place="margin">n="*" D Milborn Deane of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> Deane then <hi>aſsiſting,</hi> fearing to diſtemper his pained <hi>head,</hi> with any lowd <hi>voice,</hi> his <hi>highneſse</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly calleth and willeth him to ſpeake <hi>more openly,</hi> ſuch was his <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>harty</hi> reſpect to his <hi>religious</hi> prayers. As alſo his <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>delight</hi> to <hi>receaue</hi> thoſe <hi>heavenly</hi> plentifull <hi>inſtructions,</hi> and to <hi>partake</hi> in thoſe holy <hi>powerfull devotions</hi> of the moſt <hi>Reverend Archb.</hi> who daily did both viſit, and perfect that <hi>good worke</hi> in him, ſo that <hi>neither</hi> the <hi>dulneſſe</hi> of the <hi>diſeaſe, drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of his <hi>head, dimneſſe</hi> of his <hi>eies,</hi> or <hi>diſturbances</hi> of his whole <hi>afflicted</hi> body, could hinder the <hi>divine part</hi> from her <hi>great ſolace</hi> in ſo great ſorrow.</p>
            <p>Learne hence yee <hi>profane, vnſeaſoned ſoules,</hi> who never name <hi>God</hi> but in <hi>oathes,</hi> never thinke vpon him, but in <hi>extremitie,</hi> yee <hi>ſenceleſse graceleſſe</hi> Gallants, to whom <hi>will</hi> is a <hi>law, appetite</hi> a <hi>Lord, reaſon</hi> a <hi>ſervant,</hi> and <hi>religion</hi> a <hi>drudge:</hi> a <hi>time</hi> will <hi>come,</hi> when you ſhall not knowe how to thinke vpon <hi>God,</hi> becauſe yee <hi>beginne</hi> to learne but <hi>then;</hi> the Apoſtle queſtioneth you, how can yee call vpon <hi>him,</hi> in whom yee haue not <hi>beleeued?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177261:13"/>Thinke you to liue with <hi>him,</hi> whom yee haue reiected from <hi>liuing</hi> with you, becauſe, this is the <hi>ende</hi> of all knowledge, <hi>entertaine</hi> yee this knowledge only, in the end of your <hi>liues?</hi> How many <hi>great</hi> ones haue ſlept their <hi>ſleepe</hi> and found nothing, when <hi>lying</hi> vpon the <hi>altar</hi> of their <hi>death beds,</hi> to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> their <hi>bodies</hi> for the ſinne of their <hi>ſoules,</hi> the <hi>hart</hi> like a peece of <hi>dead</hi> fleſh, hath beene without <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>loue,</hi> of <hi>feare,</hi> of <hi>care,</hi> of <hi>paine,</hi> from the deafe <hi>ſtroakes</hi> of a <hi>wrath revenging co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> Theſe harts <hi>ſurbated</hi> with <hi>cares,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſurfeted</hi> with <hi>riots,</hi> as they haue no naturall <hi>traduction</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> ſo no celeſtiall <hi>infuſion</hi> of grace, <hi>Mercury</hi> hath gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their braine, <hi>Iupiter</hi> their liver, <hi>Mars</hi> their gall, <hi>Saturne</hi> their ſpleene, <note place="margin">Laur. Anat.</note> but <hi>Sol</hi> the ſunne of <hi>righteouſnes</hi> had never any <hi>power</hi> over, never any <hi>place</hi> in their harts. O <hi>ſtony, ſteely</hi> hardnes of <hi>hearts,</hi> which no <hi>blowes</hi> can <hi>breake,</hi> to whom <hi>nothing</hi> ſhall be <hi>granted,</hi> though it may bee <hi>required,</hi> becauſe <hi>nothing</hi> was <hi>performed</hi> which was commanded. O <hi>loathſome</hi> ſoule, <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>bare,</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> can al thy compaſſing <hi>friends</hi> infuſe no one teare into thine <hi>eyes,</hi> one drop of <hi>comfort</hi> into thy <hi>hart,</hi> one repentant <hi>ſighe</hi> from thy <hi>ſoule,</hi> one graine of <hi>faith</hi> into thy <hi>ſpirit,</hi> one mite of <hi>mercy,</hi> one iot of <hi>ioy</hi> into thy <hi>conſcience?</hi> O <hi>dumbe dumpe,</hi> ſhall the world Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho thy <hi>ſinnes,</hi> hell eccho thy <hi>ſorrowes?</hi> Art thou in thy paſſage, and knoweſt that no ſooner is thy <hi>candle</hi> out, but the <hi>large</hi> hiſtory of thy <hi>life,</hi> ſhall be <hi>openly</hi> read? Is the <hi>impoſtume</hi> of thy <hi>lies, luſts, oathes, oppreſsions,</hi> now <hi>breaking,</hi> the vaile of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> now to be <hi>remoued,</hi> and thy <hi>memory</hi> to become as <hi>odious</hi> to all men, as thy life
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177261:13"/>was <hi>tedious</hi> to <hi>good</hi> men, haſt thou beene <hi>vnhappy</hi> in thy <hi>birth, vngodly</hi> in thy <hi>being,</hi> and muſt thou bee <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious</hi> in thy <hi>end.</hi> Conſider this, ô all yee that forget <hi>God,</hi> leaſt he ſuddainely take <hi>yee away,</hi> when there ſhall be none to <hi>helpe you,</hi> ſtrike of all <hi>delaies,</hi> which haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>devoured</hi> too much of the <hi>good</hi> time. Caſt <hi>anker,</hi> ſee if you may <hi>ſhun</hi> the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, as <hi>eminent,</hi> as <hi>immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> ſhake of the <hi>viper,</hi> avoid the <hi>enimy</hi> &amp; the <hi>ave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger,</hi> fly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> like to fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>you,</hi> leaſt that <hi>time,</hi> which yet yee may take, <hi>overtake yee,</hi> and then, yee haue <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther power</hi> to reſiſt, nor <hi>patience</hi> to beare, nor <hi>place</hi> to avoid.</p>
            <p>Let not <hi>hoary</hi> ſinnes, bring home <hi>heavy</hi> horrours, <hi>ſeaſon</hi> your <hi>ſelues, bath</hi> and <hi>embalme</hi> your <hi>ſoules,</hi> leaſt your <hi>bodies</hi> be their <hi>ſepulchers,</hi> and you, their <hi>murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers:</hi> begin early, if the <hi>ſixt</hi> houre be paſt, overſlip not the <hi>ninth,</hi> if the <hi>ninth</hi> be paſt, foreſlow not the <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth,</hi> ſtay not til the <hi>laſt</hi> houre, for he that doth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, doth not all times giue a <hi>daies wages</hi> for an <hi>houres worke; Qui promiſit poenitenti veniam, non promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit omni peccanti poenitentiam.</hi> Looke vpon that <hi>Prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly patterne</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> who in <hi>young</hi> yeares, being <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>devout, ſtedfaſt</hi> in <hi>faith, ioyfull</hi> through <hi>hope, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in <hi>charitie,</hi> hath paſſed the <hi>waues</hi> of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>world,</hi> and is finally come to the <hi>land</hi> of everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <hi>life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 And ſweet <hi>Prince!</hi> how willingly did HE ſubmit himſelfe, both to his <hi>viſitation,</hi> &amp; to the <hi>end therof,</hi> his <hi>death!</hi> when, lifting vp his <hi>minde</hi> to <hi>heaven,</hi> he <hi>diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> that ſo <hi>bright,</hi> and <hi>beautifull</hi> glory, and <hi>contemned</hi> al
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177261:14"/>things on <hi>earth,</hi> enfolded in a <hi>miſtie</hi> darkneſſe. <hi>Divine</hi> Eagle! piercing beyond the orbe of the <hi>ſun,</hi> when neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting in paines the <hi>body,</hi> which was to be a <hi>neſt</hi> of <hi>wormes,</hi> he deſireth in <hi>ioies</hi> to ſatisfie his <hi>ſoule,</hi> which was to be a <hi>Companion</hi> of <hi>Angels. Heroicall</hi> ſpirit! who, willingly entred the <hi>Combat</hi> with the laſt <hi>enimy,</hi> that is to be deſtroied, <hi>Death,</hi> when, vpon the <hi>Vigil</hi> of his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture,</hi> being viſited by that moſt Reverend <hi>Prelate</hi> the <hi>Archb.</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>religiouſly,</hi> queſtioned by his <hi>Grace,</hi> whether, he could willingly ſubmit himſelfe, to the <hi>will</hi> of God, ſo far, as the <hi>ſtroak</hi> of death, his <hi>highnes</hi> replyed, <hi>yes willingly, with all my heart,</hi> and though not with ſo great <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>tongue,</hi> as <hi>loue</hi> in <hi>heart,</hi> manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted hereby, that he was not ſo ſure to <hi>dy,</hi> as to be <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red,</hi> &amp; ſo outfaced his <hi>death,</hi> with his <hi>reſurrection,</hi> with his ever-living <hi>loue</hi> of ever-laſting <hi>life.</hi> O <hi>heroicall!</hi> nay more, O <hi>Angelicall</hi> ſpirit! <hi>fined</hi> and <hi>poliſhed</hi> in this <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi> of his <hi>affliction,</hi> that ſo <hi>freely,</hi> ſo <hi>faithfully</hi> is readie to forſake all, and to follow the <hi>Lambe whither ſoever he goeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7.</note> who with white hands and a cleane ſoule was fit to ſerue and to attend his <hi>Saviour,</hi> yea even then, to ſing with <hi>Simeon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2.28.</note>
               <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace. Then,</hi> I ſay, <hi>when</hi> the earth partaked ſo much of the <hi>beauty</hi> of <hi>heaven,</hi> ſo many <hi>delights,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>pleaſures,</hi> ſo many <hi>Triumphant,</hi> magnificent <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheys,</hi> for the <hi>ioyning</hi> of thoſe two royal Virgin <hi>riuers, Thames</hi> and <hi>Rhene,</hi> when the Gratious, vertuous <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> his highneſſe <hi>ſiſter</hi> was al glorious, her cloathing of wrought <hi>gold,</hi> when ſhee was to be <hi>brought</hi> to her Illuſtrious <hi>Palatine,</hi> in rayments of needle worke, the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177261:14"/>
               <hi>Virgins,</hi> that were her <hi>fellowes,</hi> to beare her <hi>Companie,</hi> when with all <hi>ioy</hi> and <hi>gladneſſe</hi> ſhee was to be <hi>brought</hi> to enter into her Princes <hi>Palace,</hi> that in ſteed of her <hi>Parents,</hi> ſhee might haue <hi>children,</hi> whom ſhee might make <hi>Princes</hi> in forraine <hi>lands.</hi> Then, when <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> looked downe from <hi>heaven,</hi> and all the <hi>Christian</hi> world, reſulted with ioyfull <hi>acclamation,</hi> ſome fewe <hi>Curs of Antichriſt</hi> excepted. Then, that even then, this <hi>bleſſed Prince,</hi> to be willing to leaue the <hi>world,</hi> and his happy <hi>ſoule</hi> to be <hi>contented,</hi> to be <hi>looſed</hi> from the <hi>fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of the fleſh? How ſhould it amaze thoſe <hi>ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> Moles, who deſire to haue their <hi>portion</hi> ſtill in this <hi>life,</hi> crying <hi>faciamus his tabernacula!</hi> Who when <hi>Death</hi> ſerveth the execution vpon <hi>them</hi> are moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly <hi>drawne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 17.</note> and pulled from worldly <hi>delights,</hi> as beaſts from <hi>their dennes,</hi> with <hi>malevolence</hi> &amp; <hi>violence,</hi> roaring out as <hi>lamentable</hi> a <hi>farewell</hi> to their ſoules as <hi>Adrianus</hi> the Romane Emperour, who cryed out <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimula, vagula, blandula, &amp;c.</hi> That his <hi>fondling</hi> and <hi>dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> ſoule was now <hi>fleeting,</hi> &amp; he knew not vnto what <hi>darkneſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>danger</hi> it ſhould paſſe, where now ſhoulde be hits <hi>lodging, now,</hi> that it was <hi>to looſe</hi> hits former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and <hi>ſporting,</hi> he knew not the <hi>pace,</hi> the <hi>place,</hi> the <hi>paſſage,</hi> the entertainment, how farre was he from him, <hi>whoſe motto was, Nec pudet viuere, nec piget mori,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the <hi>Saints</hi> of God, that know they are but <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, diſſolued, gathered</hi> to their <hi>fathers, fallen</hi> a ſleepe, their <hi>life</hi> is hid for a <hi>time,</hi> that they <hi>lay downe</hi> their <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles,</hi> lie downe in <hi>peace,</hi> ſleepe in the <hi>Lord,</hi> reſt in <hi>hope,</hi> wait their <hi>change;</hi> that <hi>death,</hi> is only a <hi>ferry,</hi> a <hi>boat,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177261:15"/>a <hi>bridge</hi> to convay them into another <hi>place,</hi> or as a <hi>Groome,</hi> that lights a taper into another <hi>roome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ô humane witchcraft! that ſo <hi>enchanteth</hi> thoſe two divinely poliſhed tables of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the <hi>wil</hi> &amp; <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, cheating</hi> the <hi>affections</hi> in the one, <hi>checking</hi> the <hi>meditations</hi> of the other. Why, do not the gallant <hi>walking Ghoſts,</hi> of this <hi>godleſſe-age</hi> provide more <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</hi> to entertaine the <hi>divorce</hi> &amp; <hi>diſſolution</hi> of their <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> frame? why, ſo <hi>dayly</hi> do they incur, the <hi>death</hi> of both parts, when as their <hi>defluxion,</hi> and conſuming <hi>courſe</hi> is daily manifeſted? every <hi>minute</hi> they liue, being a <hi>steppe</hi> vnto <hi>death,</hi> every action <hi>pulling</hi> away ſome part of their <hi>beloved</hi> life, when like a <hi>candle</hi> continually <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> they are <hi>howrely</hi> dying, and yet, as <hi>vnwilling</hi> to die, as <hi>weake</hi> to reſiſt <hi>death;</hi> the head a <hi>ſkull,</hi> the breath <hi>ſmoake,</hi> the eie <hi>water,</hi> the braine <hi>dirt,</hi> the hart <hi>duſt,</hi> the body a <hi>houſe of clay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scal. Exer. 148.</note> and men themſelues are not <hi>men,</hi> but <hi>peeces</hi> and <hi>fragments</hi> of men, as <hi>Scaliger</hi> told <hi>Carda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and no waies to <hi>paſſe</hi> to <hi>life</hi> but by the gate of <hi>death</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> could not paſſe to <hi>Caanan</hi> but by the <hi>dead ſea;</hi> and as <hi>an ancient</hi> compareth our <hi>body</hi> diſpoſed into the <hi>fower</hi> humors vnto the <hi>veile</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of the 4. <hi>Colours,</hi> as, this vaile muſt be <hi>removed,</hi> before the <hi>entrance</hi> can be <hi>obtained,</hi> into the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> ſo, muſt the body put of <hi>mortality,</hi> to indue it ſelfe with <hi>immortality.</hi> But the <hi>fleeting Meteors,</hi> of this <hi>fond</hi> age, neglect the <hi>Contemplation</hi> hereof, and <hi>being</hi> no more able to <hi>abide</hi> death, then <hi>quiet</hi> in thinking on the feare of <hi>death,</hi> they <hi>wiſh,</hi> to fly even from <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues,</hi> and to be <hi>diſcharged,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being <hi>guided</hi> by ſo ill a gueſt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177261:15"/>as their <hi>owne ſoule,</hi> they wiſh their <hi>portion</hi> to continue in this <hi>life,</hi> they can be <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent,</hi> to ſtay here <hi>for ever.</hi> The baſe <hi>wealth,</hi> falſe <hi>pleaſures,</hi> vaine <hi>hopes,</hi> lying <hi>promiſes,</hi> fained <hi>friendſhip,</hi> ſhort <hi>glory,</hi> fading <hi>beauty</hi> of this dull and <hi>dungeon-like</hi> life, yeelds them <hi>ſufficient ſatisfaction;</hi> otherwiſe to be ſequeſtred from theſe <hi>itching toies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching ioies,</hi> and to leaue the <hi>world,</hi> they are moſt <hi>loathſomly</hi> loath, they anſwere, they know, where they <hi>are,</hi> whither they ſhall <hi>goe</hi> they know not, and herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the inſtant of their <hi>tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſmigration</hi> they are ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to <hi>leaue</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> hence is it that they begin to <hi>feele</hi> the <hi>flames</hi> of Hell before they goe <hi>downe</hi> to the <hi>graue,</hi> before them <hi>horror,</hi> behinde them <hi>terror,</hi> on the one ſide <hi>ſinne,</hi> on the other <hi>ſhame,</hi> fire in the <hi>hand,</hi> a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent at the <hi>heart,</hi> terrors of the <hi>night,</hi> ſting of <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> feare of <hi>hell,</hi> torture them, and, their <hi>vnwillingnes</hi> to <hi>die</hi> is moſt willing to <hi>torment</hi> them. But I proceed, my ſubiect is ſorrow, whom I follow.</p>
            <p n="10">10 How ſorrowful a day, was this <hi>Vigil</hi> of his <hi>death?</hi> How <hi>watry,</hi> that <hi>day,</hi> the 5. of <hi>November,</hi> which ſhould haue beene the day of <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>fury,</hi> if that <hi>Tragedy,</hi> which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and hell <hi>plotted,</hi> had been <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted!</hi> How was this <hi>day,</hi> the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>Iubile</hi> for <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance!</hi> I ſay how was the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> thereof changed by this <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> of the Princely <hi>ſunne!</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> even then viſiting vs, <note place="margin">Lament, 2.22.</note> as <hi>Ieremy</hi> complaineth in the <hi>Lamentations, Lord, thou haſt called vs in a ſolemne day, and now terrors are round about vs.</hi> A <hi>day</hi> that at the inſtitution thereof did <hi>occaſion</hi> more cauſe of <hi>ioy,</hi> to vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ordinary day of <hi>deliuerance</hi> to the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177261:16"/>our deliverance <hi>greater,</hi> our <hi>enimies</hi> more <hi>cruell,</hi> their <hi>ſnares</hi> more <hi>fearefull,</hi> the <hi>miſcheefe</hi> more <hi>miſerable,</hi> the <hi>miſery</hi> more <hi>generall,</hi> and the <hi>proiect</hi> more <hi>horrid,</hi> and <hi>terrible</hi> then ever any, we read of among <hi>Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Graecians</hi> or <hi>Barbarians,</hi> or the <hi>hiſtory</hi> of any <hi>eſtate</hi> hath read, heard, or regiſtred in times <hi>Chronology.</hi> A day, wherein they cryed of <hi>Zion, downe with it, downe with it even to the ground.</hi> Wherein the <hi>Oracles</hi> of our wiſdome, the <hi>Chariots</hi> of our <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the ſacred <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of our <hi>Clergy</hi> had beene devoured, the <hi>learned Guardians</hi> of our <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> the whole <hi>eſtate</hi> of our <hi>weale-publike,</hi> by a publicke <hi>woe,</hi> had beene <hi>blaſted</hi> and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and conſumed. A <hi>day</hi> that ſhould haue been <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to the fowleſt <hi>monſter,</hi> and monſtrous <hi>plot,</hi> that ever was purpoſed or performed, <hi>facinus tale quod nec Poeta fingere, nec Hiſtrio ſonare, nec mimus imitari pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> even <hi>in that day,</hi> wherein wee were freed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by a <hi>miraculous hand,</hi> from this <hi>hell-borne</hi> horror intended againſt vs. O how was <hi>this daie</hi> altered, by the publicke <hi>ſorrow</hi> for <hi>vertues</hi> ſickneſſe! This <hi>fift day feare</hi> poſſeſſed City and Court; a day, that though <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> and <hi>Heſiod,</hi> count to bee moſt infortunate, yet was never ominous or inauſpitious to vs; witnes the gracious <hi>preſervation</hi> of the <hi>Lords Annointed</hi> on the 5 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> and this 5 of <hi>November.</hi> Now many &amp; hearty prayers were in <hi>fiery Chariots</hi> ſent vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to implore divine maieſtie, that <hi>this day</hi> we might not be <hi>led into the temptation</hi> of ſuch a tempeſtuous <hi>ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke</hi> as the loſſe of our <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heſiod. Virgil.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Heſiod;</hi> and <hi>Quintam fuge</hi> is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177261:16"/>
               <hi>Virgils</hi> caution; and <hi>Rhodiginus</hi> giveth the reaſon, <note place="margin">Coel. Rodig. lib. 8. cap. 9.</note> that vpon the <hi>fift</hi> day the <hi>furies</hi> doe <hi>governe,</hi> it being the <hi>day</hi> of their <hi>birth.</hi> The <hi>fift day,</hi> the <hi>Gyants</hi> began their <hi>warres</hi> againſt <hi>heaven,</hi> ſhipwracks, earthquakes, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, devaſtations, being even proper to <hi>this day;</hi> and the <hi>Brumalia</hi> being kept in the ſame month of <hi>Nove<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and about the 5 day, had the dedication, <hi>à ſonitu to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitrus &amp; fulminis.</hi> Yet neither this <hi>month,</hi> nor this <hi>day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſp. de ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Feſt. Novemb.</note> were ever yet vnhappy to vs, til <hi>now;</hi> and <hi>now</hi> beganne we to tremble, though we had ſcaped the <hi>fift daies fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and the <hi>Brumalia,</hi> the <hi>Winters</hi> feaſt, which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, yet now the <hi>Ioy of our heart was humbled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam 5.15.</note>
               <hi>and feare was on every ſide.</hi> But <hi>Thou continueſt holy O thou worſhip of Iſrael.</hi> O <hi>Lord,</hi> let it never be forgotten, that thou didſt pleaſe to ſpare and forbeare the great <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of this <hi>day,</hi> and <hi>this day</hi> didſt not ſo <hi>overſhadowe</hi> vs, with <hi>ſorrow,</hi> as to take away our <hi>Ioſias,</hi> in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britie of our <hi>preſervation,</hi> to extinguiſh our <hi>ioy</hi> vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by <hi>Hadadrimmons lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A meditation, that ſhould ſtirre vp al thoſe vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnthankfull ſoules among vs, who neglect the <hi>Lords</hi> favour, and the remembrance of his holineſſe, in the <hi>deliverance</hi> of this day. It was his infinite mercy that this day he let not our enimies laugh vs to ſcorn or to triumph over vs, but deferred Prince HENRYES death one day further. Yet certainely hee ſuffered this heavy iudgement to fall vpon vs ſo neere to this time, becauſe we are ſo forgetfull of his marvailous <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance</hi> from the <hi>dangerous engins</hi> prepared againſt that time. It is not vnworthy the obſervation, <note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> that moſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177261:17"/>of the great <hi>iudgements</hi> fell vpon <hi>Iſrael</hi> vpon the <hi>daies</hi> of their <hi>ſolemne feaſts,</hi> ſurely for the <hi>prophaneſſe</hi> and <hi>vnthankfulneſſe</hi> of them, for thoſe <hi>bleſsings</hi> receaued, which occaſioned the <hi>inſtitution</hi> of thoſe <hi>feaſts.</hi> And why ſhould wee not forever hereafter ſtand in awe, trembling, and fearing, how the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>afflicted</hi> vs ſo <hi>neere</hi> our <hi>ſolemn feaſt day.</hi> And though he had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs from the <hi>violence</hi> and malevolence of <hi>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,</hi> yet, if we turne not, he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>whet his ſword</hi> &amp; <hi>bend his bow,</hi> as he did by that <hi>arrow</hi> that ſtrook <hi>Iſraels Ioſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 It is as true as terrible, <hi>iudgement</hi> may be <hi>prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> but when the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>ſpoken,</hi> by no power it can be <hi>avoided.</hi> The <hi>ſixt day</hi> enſued, which as if it had had a divine <hi>diſpenſation</hi> to breake the <hi>ſixt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, ſlew</hi> our PRINCE. A day, that hath beene <hi>Principibus infeſta &amp; infauſta;</hi> witneſſe the death of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, the ſixt of <hi>Aprill;<note place="margin">1199</note> Henry</hi> the ſecond, the 6 of <hi>Iuly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1189</note>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, the 6 of <hi>Iuly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1307</note> &amp; our laſt <hi>Edward,</hi> bleſſed K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. on the 6 of <hi>Iuly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1553</note> as alſo this 6 day of <hi>November,</hi> wherein our, <hi>Iulium ſydus, Prince</hi> HENRYES ſunne did ſet.</p>
            <p>Divine ſoule! how readily did it <hi>moue</hi> to its <hi>Center,</hi> &amp; how conſtantly! all the <hi>ſtormes</hi> could not <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> the <hi>arke</hi> of his <hi>faith,</hi> all the <hi>ſurges</hi> could not <hi>ſinke</hi> his pretious <hi>ſoule.</hi> He continued victoriouſly <hi>Conſtant,</hi> &amp; is aſſured, to <hi>ſee the Lord</hi> in the <hi>land</hi> of the <hi>living.</hi> The <hi>beames</hi> of his faith did <hi>reflect</hi> vpon him, and kept life beyond life in him, when the laſt <hi>ſymptomes,</hi> the <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers</hi> of death appeared, in that diſmall <hi>period,</hi> of that <hi>fatall day,</hi> the <hi>violence</hi> of <hi>convulſions,</hi> and <hi>fury,</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177261:17"/>extremity of the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> appearing then moſt terribly, becauſe it was never to appeare againe. In that ſparke of life, his laſt &amp; beſt <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> the moſt <hi>Religious,</hi> moſt <hi>Reverend Archb.</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> being his <hi>highneſſe</hi> heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembrancer by many hearty, &amp; holy <hi>exhortations</hi> to <hi>aſsure</hi> him with aſſured <hi>Constancy,</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> mercy, to <hi>lift</hi> vp his <hi>hart</hi> to prepare him to meete the <hi>Lord;</hi> and calling more <hi>earneſtly</hi> and lowdly, becauſe the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> of <hi>ſpeech</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> were deprived of vſe, his <hi>highneſſe</hi> being earneſtly moved to manifeſt by <hi>ſignes</hi> his <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of theſe divine <hi>exhortations</hi> and his <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> herevnto, he <hi>lifted vp</hi> his holy <hi>hands</hi> vnited, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards his <hi>eies bent</hi> to <hi>heaven,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence not long after appeared, in his deliverance, his <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learne hence all yee vnmindfull, vnfaithful, vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, weather-beaten <hi>worldlings,</hi> who, like <hi>reeds</hi> toſſed of the <hi>winde,</hi> never co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in one <hi>ſtay,</hi> whom the leaſt <hi>blaſt</hi> of <hi>affliction</hi> doth ſo amate and amaze, as that <hi>God</hi> is forgotten, and being vnbeleeving <hi>Scepticks, beleeue</hi> no more then yee <hi>ſee,</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> no more then yee <hi>feele,</hi> and therefore are ſure to want the Continuance of <hi>Conſtancie</hi> at your deaths, becauſe you were never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it in your life. When all your <hi>members</hi> and <hi>faculties</hi> are <hi>ſurpriſed,</hi> all <hi>paines</hi> &amp; perplexities <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged,</hi> when the <hi>ſorrowes</hi> of <hi>death compaſſe</hi> yee <hi>about,</hi> &amp; the <hi>floods</hi> of <hi>wickedneſſe make</hi> yee <hi>afraid;</hi> then how hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid will it be, that out of all your former lifes <hi>extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> no one <hi>drop,</hi> either of Comfort, or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance, may be <hi>diſtild!</hi> When the aking <hi>head,</hi> panting <hi>hart,</hi> faultring <hi>tongue,</hi> ſhortning <hi>breath,</hi> beating <hi>veines,</hi> crazed <hi>minde,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177261:18"/>and crackt <hi>memory</hi> ſhall diſturbe, and diſtract all your <hi>facult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> and not only your heavenly, but even earthly <hi>cogitations;</hi> when the dumbe <hi>mouth,</hi> numbed <hi>hands,</hi> ſtiffe <hi>ioints,</hi> pale <hi>lips,</hi> vaniſhing <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and expiring <hi>life,</hi> be the forerunners of a dolefull fearefull <hi>death;</hi> and the <hi>want</hi> of a religious ſettled conſtant <hi>memory,</hi> ſhall then bring the <hi>woe</hi> of a <hi>wanton minde,</hi> and yee ſhall by a <hi>ſcourge</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> receiue a beginning in this life of your full <hi>torments</hi> in the <hi>flames</hi> of <hi>hell,</hi> the eternall <hi>iustice</hi> making you <hi>executioners</hi> of your owne <hi>faults:</hi> the <hi>hart</hi> &amp; <hi>hope,</hi> of life being but a <hi>bubble,</hi> a <hi>ſmoake,</hi> a <hi>lie,</hi> a <hi>fury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſd 5. Eſay. 28. Prov. 11. Iob. 11.</note> as <hi>Salomon, Eſay,</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> haue deſcribed it, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſweet <hi>ſolace</hi> of the ſoule, and that <hi>aſsurance,</hi> which the Saints haue in all your <hi>anguiſhes</hi> and <hi>extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> neither obtaining <hi>acceptance</hi> with God nor <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> from God, a <hi>Graue-ſtone</hi> lying vpon your <hi>harts, ſealed</hi> with the ſenſe of Gods <hi>iudgements, preſſed downe</hi> with the <hi>rubbiſh</hi> and ruines of the <hi>decayed monuments</hi> of ancient <hi>tranſgreſſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> your <hi>foundation</hi> laid not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>rocke,</hi> but on the <hi>ſands,</hi> and in the <hi>ſea,</hi> where <hi>waues</hi> and <hi>windes beat</hi> on every ſide, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thoſe old <hi>friends,</hi> but new <hi>enimies</hi> lie in <hi>ambuſh,</hi> the corrupters of <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſeducers of <hi>will,</hi> Traitors of <hi>vertue,</hi> flatterers of <hi>vice,</hi> Pyoners of <hi>Courage,</hi> murtherers of <hi>Comfort,</hi> &amp; the extinguiſhers of all <hi>peace in conſcience</hi> or <hi>ioy</hi> in ſpirit. Whereas to, a <hi>reſolved</hi> ſoule, to a <hi>Conſtant</hi> Chriſtian, even in the pangs of <hi>death</hi> he then chiefly, ſeemeth to be the <hi>liuely</hi> and <hi>louely image</hi> of his <hi>maker,</hi> having his <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>vnderstanding</hi> cleere, his <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> ordinate, his ſenſuall <hi>faculties</hi> not only <hi>reſtrained</hi> from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177261:18"/>evill, but <hi>conſtrained</hi> to be <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to do good: and howſoever his corporall ſtate be in an <hi>Ecclipſe,</hi> &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as much in <hi>ſenſe,</hi> as it aboundeth in <hi>ſorrow,</hi> yet his ſoule is triumphing, &amp; <hi>reioycing</hi> in <hi>God</hi> his <hi>Saviour,</hi> &amp; ready to ſing his <hi>Nunc dimittis,</hi> as this <hi>Princely Saint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 And now <hi>death</hi> Natures <hi>midwife,</hi> began her final act of <hi>diſſolution,</hi> &amp; this fatall day, <hi>friday,</hi> (a day, which long before, his <hi>highneſſe</hi> accounted diſmall) proved to be the day of <hi>blackneſſe</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> a day of <hi>clowds</hi> &amp; <hi>gloomiſhnes,</hi> there never was ſince the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the like; and <hi>Lord,</hi> let never be the like any more, after it, even to the yeares of many generations! Now the infallible <hi>ſignes</hi> of vnſatisfiable <hi>death</hi> approaching, the diſiointing <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vulſions,</hi> &amp; trembling <hi>agonies</hi> came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, <hi>Nature</hi> waſting like a dying <hi>Lampe,</hi> &amp; in that day, his <hi>ſtarres</hi> begin to be <hi>darkned,</hi> the <hi>keepers</hi> of his <hi>houſe</hi> to <hi>tremble,</hi> the <hi>ſtrong men</hi> to <hi>bow</hi> themſelues, the <hi>grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to ceaſe, they that looke out of the <hi>window</hi> to be darkened. Now the <hi>ſiluer Cord</hi> is ready to be <hi>looſed,</hi> the <hi>golden pitcher breaking</hi> at the fountaine, and the <hi>wheele breaking</hi> at the Ceſterne. Now, now HEE is going to his <hi>long home,</hi> and the <hi>mourners</hi> go about in the ſtreet. <hi>O miſeram faciem orbis!</hi> O wofull countenance of a Court, that now appeared! the <hi>Eccho</hi> and reclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>ſighes, ſobs,</hi> the throwes of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> of <hi>outcryes,</hi> and vnſpeakeable <hi>Lamentation,</hi> ſounded not only in that wofull <hi>houſe,</hi> and therein in the <hi>Chambers</hi> of death, but in all the <hi>Court,</hi> all the <hi>city,</hi> men paſſing along by each other, as if they had bin come out of the <hi>graues. Teares groanes,</hi> heavy <hi>lookes,</hi> diſſheveld <hi>lockes,</hi> and <hi>lamentations</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177261:19"/>filling all places; <hi>ſpeach,</hi> &amp; <hi>life,</hi> ſeeming to be <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to men, the ſaddeſt <hi>time,</hi> &amp; ſableſt <hi>world,</hi> that ever our <hi>Country</hi> knew. It exceeds <hi>invention</hi> to <hi>imagine</hi> it, and is able to caſt a perpetual <hi>dampe</hi> vpon the <hi>vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> that ſhal <hi>conceiue</hi> it: my hand, pen, heart, all my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties ſinke vnder this burden, I lacke <hi>Agamemnons</hi> vaile. The delight of mankinde, &amp; expectation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is expiring, <hi>where, how, whence</hi> is Comfort, to bee had? I ſhal never forget ever to pity thoſe poore ſouls, with wringing <hi>hands</hi> &amp; breaking <hi>harts,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſhrikes,</hi> and <hi>outcries</hi> are able to pearce <hi>Adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> Are <hi>ſins</hi> more prevailing, then <hi>prayers?</hi> Where is the power and <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> of <hi>praier?</hi> which <hi>opened,</hi> and <hi>ſhut,</hi> and <hi>ſealed</hi> vp <hi>heaven,</hi> brought downe <hi>fire,</hi> and ſtaied the <hi>ſunne</hi> in the firmament. No <hi>hope,</hi> no <hi>helpe,</hi> all <hi>miracles</hi> ceaſed? No <hi>balme</hi> in Gilead, nothing in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>extracts</hi> of nature, no <hi>Elixir</hi> in Art to recover, to repaire this ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverable <hi>conſumption?</hi> It was <hi>providence,</hi> that diſpoſed it, and doth <hi>ſilence</hi> queſtion. But was the <hi>charge</hi> ſo ſtrict, as that the great <hi>Tyrant Death</hi> would ſmite, neither ſmall, nor great, but <hi>Iſraels</hi> Prince, the <hi>Ioſhua, Ioſiah,</hi> Maieſties <hi>firſt borne,</hi> Religions <hi>ſecond?</hi> Muſt the <hi>Roſe</hi> be <hi>blemiſhed,</hi> before it was fully <hi>bloomed?</hi> or the <hi>fig tree blaſted,</hi> before it was time to bring forth <hi>fruit?</hi> O <hi>crueltie</hi> of that ſavage monſter <hi>Death! O Death,</hi> thou <hi>child</hi> of ſinne, and <hi>father</hi> of confuſion! haſt thou not already triumphed enough, in funerall ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? thy <hi>applauſe</hi> in the <hi>cries</hi> of widdowes, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, by the <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>deſolation</hi> of thy <hi>vniverſall</hi> dominion; that as many <hi>ages,</hi> as haue beene ſince the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177261:19"/>
               <hi>world</hi> was <hi>created,</hi> ſo many <hi>conqueſts,</hi> haſt thou obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and yet thy all devouring <hi>throat,</hi> the graue vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied? But againe I ſee the finger of <hi>providence</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ſilence, forbidding <hi>queſtion.</hi> Yet my eares <hi>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> with the dolefull <hi>tune</hi> of that wofull <hi>time.</hi> The <hi>bell</hi> now <hi>calleth</hi> him to the <hi>triumphant</hi> Church; by <hi>day Death</hi> durſt not approach, by <hi>night</hi> he vndertakes this <hi>deed</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> The redoubled <hi>ſound</hi> of that <hi>ſolemne,</hi> but <hi>ſorrowfull knell</hi> ſtrooke all hearts, with a <hi>chilling, killing</hi> feare; now, <hi>hope</hi> was without <hi>helpe;</hi> the <hi>ayer</hi> was <hi>troubled</hi> with the ſcriching <hi>outcries,</hi> and all <hi>knees</hi> bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all <hi>faces</hi> plentifully bedewed, the <hi>world</hi> in an <hi>extaſie,</hi> as if ſome <hi>eſpeciall part</hi> of <hi>nature</hi> were <hi>diſſoluing.</hi> Now were the laſt <hi>prayers</hi> of the <hi>family,</hi> who without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion were all that <hi>day</hi> aſſiſted by many <hi>honourable,</hi> and <hi>infinite</hi> lamentably ſobbing <hi>ſoules;</hi> whereof the <hi>Chappell, veſtry, entry,</hi> and whole <hi>Court</hi> were ful, all ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with ſtrong <hi>cries,</hi> weeping <hi>eyes,</hi> &amp; bleeding <hi>hearts</hi> did commend his bleſſed <hi>ſoule,</hi> to be bathed in the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood</hi> of his <hi>Saviour.</hi> And ſo not long after <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, patiently, bleſſedly</hi> he <hi>expired,</hi> and yeelded his <hi>ſpirit</hi> into the hands of his immortall maker. Even then, when that inauſpicious <hi>aſpect</hi> of the <hi>planets</hi> did <hi>porte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> ſome ominous <hi>diſaſter,</hi> when only <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> appeared aboue, and <hi>Sol, Mars, Mercury, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> lay hid below, not daring to be <hi>witneſſes</hi> of that heavie and horrid <hi>effect</hi> of that horrible <hi>coniunction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learne hence all yee <hi>firre trees,</hi> that <hi>Cedars</hi> may fal, and <hi>Princes</hi> the <hi>Gods</hi> of the <hi>earth</hi> may <hi>die.</hi> They are men, <hi>helpleſſe</hi> men, <hi>mortall</hi> men, <hi>corruptible</hi> men, in the <hi>frames</hi> of their <hi>bodies,</hi> and in the <hi>cogitations</hi> of their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177261:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>minds.</hi> Happy therefore is he, that hath the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> for his <hi>refuge!</hi> Happy is hee, whoſe <hi>hope</hi> is in the <hi>Lord</hi> his <hi>God!</hi> And bleſſed be our <hi>God,</hi> who in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceavable <hi>wiſdome</hi> of his divine <hi>wil,</hi> hath freed bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Prince HENRY from the <hi>fetters</hi> of the <hi>fleſh!</hi> Who when he had <hi>ſhewed</hi> him the <hi>world,</hi> to <hi>loath</hi> the <hi>world, enfranchiſed</hi> him from this earthly <hi>priſon</hi> and <hi>dungeon,</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> him now with <hi>greater</hi> libertie. Where being exalted in greateſt <hi>glory, hee</hi> is nowe in <hi>his</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, where there is <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of <hi>ioy,</hi> and at <hi>his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pleaſure for euermore.</hi> Where there is an immortall, immarceſſible <hi>crowne,</hi> wherewith already hee is ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in that <hi>kingdome</hi> of <hi>continuance,</hi> where <hi>ſorrow</hi> ſhal never be <hi>felt, ſickneſſe</hi> never be <hi>feared;</hi> where <hi>ioy</hi> cannot be <hi>touched</hi> with <hi>ſadneſſe,</hi> nor <hi>health tainted</hi> with <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> where there is all <hi>good,</hi> without any <hi>evill,</hi> and all <hi>trouble,</hi> all <hi>puniſhment,</hi> and all <hi>feare</hi> is done away.</p>
            <p>And finally, <hi>bleſſed</hi> bee that <hi>God,</hi> who hath out of his <hi>fountaine</hi> of <hi>goodneſſe</hi> once againe opened the <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes</hi> of the <hi>mornings mercy</hi> and reſtored a new <hi>light</hi> to thoſe ſorrowfull <hi>ſoules,</hi> who ſate in <hi>darkneſse</hi> and in the <hi>ſhadow of death;</hi> and hath reſtored the voice of <hi>ioy,</hi> and <hi>gladneſſe</hi> vnto our moſt gracious K. IAMES, and the <hi>family</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> IAMES, by the ſetling of that houſe and the happy ſhining of our <hi>day ſtarre</hi> CHARLEMAINE, the <hi>apparant heire</hi> of his bleſſed <hi>Brothers</hi> vertues and titles, the <hi>Parallel</hi> of former, and abſolute <hi>patterne</hi> of future <hi>Princes,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſtemme</hi> and <hi>ſtock</hi> long may it <hi>flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> vnder the <hi>branches</hi> of thoſe Royall <hi>Cedars,</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Parents;</hi> that ſo with much <hi>happineſſe,</hi> his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> may bring forth his <hi>fruit</hi> in due <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> to all good mens <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>Gods</hi> great <hi>glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177261:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
